<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Rich treasure in earthen vessels a sermon preached, Jan. 1, 1662/3, at the funeral of that reverend and faithful servant of Jesus Christ, Mr. James Nalton, late minister of God's word at St. Leonards Foster-lane / by T. Horton ...</title>
            <author>Horton, Thomas, d. 1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44566</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2879</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7695</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11800827</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11800827</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49381</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44566)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49381)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 535:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Rich treasure in earthen vessels a sermon preached, Jan. 1, 1662/3, at the funeral of that reverend and faithful servant of Jesus Christ, Mr. James Nalton, late minister of God's word at St. Leonards Foster-lane / by T. Horton ...</title>
                  <author>Horton, Thomas, d. 1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Nalton, James, 1600-1662.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, IV, 7 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49381:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Rich Treaſure in Earthen Veſſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached (<hi>Jan.</hi> 1. 1662/3.) at the FUNERAL OF That Reverend and faithful Servant of Jeſus Chriſt, Mr. <hi>JAMES NALTON,</hi> Late Miniſter of God's Word at St. <hi>LEONARDS Foſter-Lane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>T. HORTON,</hi> D.D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your Fathers, where are they? and the Prophets, do they live for ever?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1663.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:49381:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49381:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To</hi> the READER,</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Do here preſent unto thee a Sermon preached by a Reverend and Learned Miniſter in this City, at the Funeral of that faithful, godly, and truly conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, Mr. <hi>James Nalton,</hi> whoſe Name is as a precious Oyntment poured forth unto all the godly in this Nation: He was one of thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſons of <hi>Zion</hi> (of whom the world is not worthy) ejected by men, but now taken into a better Living by the great Biſhop of ſouls. Surely <hi>Englands</hi> ſins are very great and hainous, that have turned God and Man againſt us. Our <hi>Teachers</hi> are thrown into corners by men, and called away from us by God. Oh that our eyes could run down with Rivers of tears! but who layes this to heart? the righteous are deſpiſed, rejected, and taken away, but no man regards it; if our wreſtling <hi>Jacobs,</hi> our <hi>Moſes's</hi> in the
<pb facs="tcp:49381:3"/>gap, our praying <hi>Elijahs,</hi> our weeping <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiahs,</hi> be called home, Lord, what will become of <hi>England!</hi> whoſe prayers will be inſtrumental to remove thoſe judgments in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent, and prevent thoſe which are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent: if the mourners in <hi>Zion</hi> ceaſe from among us, ſurely then 'tis not only our duty, but our ſafety to pray for (and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently bewaile the loſs of) their lives, who are our Fathers, the chariots &amp; horſemen of England, for whoſe ſake this Nation is kept from the judgements of Sodom &amp; Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah, yet guilty of greater abominations, <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſay no more, but commend this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to thy reading, and intreat that candor from thee, that if thou findeſt any errata in words or phraſes, or any thing that ſeems imperfect, not to impute it to the reverend and learned Diſpenſer, but to the Tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber hereof So <hi>I</hi> commend thee to God, Far well.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49381:3"/>
            <head>Rich treaſure in Earthen Veſſels, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Cor. 4.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But we have this Treaſure in Earthen Veſſels, that the excellency of the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er may be of God, and not of us.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing ſo excellent or compleat in this World, but hath its diminiſhment and qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and ſomething that doth diſparage it, and abates of the excellency thereof; not the things of this World onely, but ſpiritual things in ſome ſort, as to enjoy them, and partake of them in this life, have their inconveniences and diſparagements annext, and are mingled with ſomething that abates of their worth; an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of which we have here in this preſent Scripture which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſignifies to us concerning the enjoyment of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of the Goſpel of Chriſt. He had in the verſe before the Text, told us the great priviledge that both Miniſters and others had in having the glorious Goſpel, viz. <hi>The light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſhining into our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49381:4"/>hearts; the conſideration of which is of great encouragement to us; yet adds this as a qualification of it, viz. <hi>But we have this treaſure in earthen Veſsels, &amp;c:</hi> That which doth qualifie it, is, That this excellent treaſure hath its conveyances through weak and mean perſons, men of frailty and mortality. In the words there are two main parts:
<list>
                  <item>I. The Diſpenſation it ſelf.</item>
                  <item>II. The Account of it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. The Diſpenſation it ſelf, This <hi>Treaſure</hi> we have in earthen Veſſels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. The account of it, <hi>That the excellency of the power may be of God, and not of us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall begin with the firſt, the Diſpenſation it ſelf, which hath two blanches.</p>
            <p n="1">1, The <hi>Depoſitum,</hi> the thing laid up.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Repoſitory</hi> in which this Treaſure is laid up.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Depoſitum, or thing laid up, which is a Treaſure, and what is this Treaſure, but the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt? The Goſpel is a Treaſure according to a twofold conſideration:
<list>
                  <item>In reſpect of the 1. Matter of it.</item>
                  <item>In reſpect of the 2. Miniſtry of it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Both make up a treaſure. The Matter of it, the things of the Goſpel are rich things, and the conveyances of it; the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial gifts and ability, by which the Goſpel is adminiſtred, do make up the Treaſure: 'Tis a Treaſure in both reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect of the matter of it; therefore it is we read of the <hi>Riches of Chriſt,</hi> of the <hi>Riches of the Goſpel.</hi> The Scripture makes mention of three things wherein the Goſpel is agreeable to a treaſure.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Treaſure is a thing of dignity and worth; 'tis not a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of pebbles (though many) that will make up a Treaſure; a Treaſure conſiſts of things of worth and dignity; and thus is the Goſpel; in it are contained excellent and admirable truths, the Myſteries of ſalvation by Chriſt; the doctrine of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel brings glad tydings of peace and reconciliation with God in Chriſt; there we have the gifts and graces of God; there we
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49381:4"/>have glory and immortality, &amp;c. and thoſe things in the Goſpel are adminiſtred to us: there is no ſcience in the world brings ſuch treaſure as this.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Goſpel is a treaſure for variety, abundance, and plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality. 'Tis not one thing of worth, but many that makes up a treaſure; if few, yet much worth muſt be comprehended in them; ſo in the Goſpel we have the manifold wiſdom of God, the rich treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledge The Goſpel, though it be but one for ſubſtance, yet 'tis many for improvements; 'tis a chain of many links; one faith, but divers articles of it; ſo it is a treaſure in that reſpect.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis a treaſure for its cloſeneſs; We do not open a treaſure to every one, but it is kept cloſe. The Goſpel is a ſecret myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, hidden, not revealed to every one; it is not diſcovered to carnal worldly men, though it may be revealed to them in the outward propoſition, yet not in the ſpirituality of it. <hi>But where ſhall wiſdom be found? and where is the place of underſtanding?</hi> ſaith <hi>Job, ch.</hi> 28. <hi>v.</hi> 12. The peace of the Goſpel is a treaſure hid in the field, not found by every one.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Goſpel is a treaſure in reſpect of the miniſtry of it; ſo the Apoſtle hints, 'tis not onely light, but a ſhining light, which <hi>hath ſhined into our hearts to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God,</hi> &amp;c. 'Tis a treaſure in this reſpect, <hi>viz.</hi> in the diſcovery and ſhining of it, the conveyances, the ſeveral gifts and graces of the miniſtry, by which the Goſpel is conveyed to us, makes up a treaſure; and as the Miniſtry is a treaſure, ſo the opportunities and advantages thereof are. Thus the Goſpel and the Miniſtry thereof is pretious, and ought to be eſteemed and made uſe of by us. We ſhould highly account of the Goſpel, and put a high value on it, for it is a treaſure; yea, it is a treaſure in the want of other treaſures, they are rich that are made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of it; <hi>Silver and Gold have I none</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Peter</hi> to the Crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) <hi>but ſuch as I have I give it thee:</hi> this is the priviledge of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters; though it may be, poor in reſpect of themſelves, yet are rich to others. Theſe excellent riches are committed to us, and accordingly we muſt not only make uſe of them our ſelves, but make them known to others; the Goſpel is a treaſure not for us to keep up, but to diſcover, reveal and manifeſt to others; to give the <hi>light of the glory of God,</hi> &amp;c. This is the work of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49381:5"/>We have indeed this treaſure, but not for our ſelves only, but for others; ſo we are to keep it, to preſerve and maintain it, but ſo as to be diligent to impart what is committed to us for the edification of others: <hi>Every Scribe inſtructed in the Kingdom of Heaven as a good houſholder, bringeth forth things new and old.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Goſpel is a treaſure, therefore we ought to carry our ſelves anſwerable to it: As</p>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt labour for it, be diligent in the ſearch of it, dig for it as for <hi>hidden treaſures. Lift up thy voice for underſtanding,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.2,3,4. Dig for it, you know there is a great deal of pains taken, and labour uſed to get Worldly treaſure, What would not men venture for it? they will go over Sea and Land, go through ſire and water, expoſe themſelves to all dangers for earthly treaſure, <hi>make unto themſelves friends of the Mammon of unrighteouſneſs,</hi> paſs away a great deal of time, and take a great deal of care for it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Eſteem this treaſure; this heavenly wiſdom, this Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal knowledge, even the Goſpel of Chriſt; labour to underſtand it, and have the efficacy wrough upon your hearts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Rejoyce in it; how do men rejoyce in earthly treaſure; ſo ſhould we, as the Merchant in the Goſpel when he had found the Pearl of Prize, rejoyced exceedingly; ſo we ought, as being made partakers thereof, <hi>I rejoyced at thy word, even as one that had found great ſpoyls,</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) ſo ſhould we rejoyce always in this treaſure. 'Tis ſaid of thoſe that ſate under <hi>John Baptists</hi> Miniſtry, that they rejoyced but for a while, and that is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and miſery of many. The City of <hi>Samaria</hi> when they had received the Goſpel, 'tis ſaid they had great joy, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.9.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Be careful to keep and preſerve it, for it is a treaſure, and therefore we muſt treaſure it up in our hearts; and the rather becauſe it will keep us. It keeps (as <hi>Chryſostome</hi> ſaith) the houſe where it is; other treaſures cannot ſecure themſelves, but if we keep this treaſure it will ſecure us. <hi>Diſcretion ſhall preſerve thee, and underſtanding ſhall keep thee Prov.</hi> 2.11. thus you ſee the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of this ſpiritual wiſdom. So much for the firſt thing conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable in the firſt branch. <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Depoſitum,</hi> the <hi>treaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing conſiderable is, the <hi>Repoſitory, h.e.</hi> Earthen Veſſels, or veſſels of Earth earthen Pitchers: theſe are the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitory,</hi> but we have this treaſure in <hi>earthen veſſels,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Earth</hi> is a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49381:5"/>word of diminution, and diſparagement, and that in three regards;
<list>
                  <item>1 In regard of its meaneſs and baſeneſs.</item>
                  <item>2 In regard of its foulneſs and pollution.</item>
                  <item>3 In regard of its frailty and tranſitorineſs.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis paſſing away in all theſe reſpects; theſe earthen veſſels in the Text, is to he underſtood, the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, in regard of their outward man are ſo called, and are ſo according to this threefold notion.</p>
            <p n="1">I. In regard of their meanneſs; their outſide is mean, either for perſon, or ſometimes for eſtate, body, &amp; outward deportment. This was the condition (you know) of the firſt Miniſters of Chriſt, mean and ordinary perſons outwardly God made uſe of. Nay our Maſter, our bleſſed Lord and Saviour was mean in regard of his humane birth, and reckoned of by moſt men according to his birth and parentage, So it is with the ſervants of Chriſt, they are in their perſons generally baſe, mean, low, and accordingly rendred deſpicable to the eyes of the World.</p>
            <p n="2">II. In regard of foulneſs and pollution; Miniſters are called earthen Veſſels, they have many weakneſſes, they are men ſubject to the like paſſions as others. Tis true the Miniſters of Chriſt have greater advantages then others, in regard of their education, knowledge, gifts, and imployments, being more free from thoſe deſilements and ſnares that others are intangled in: yet through the remainders of the fleſh in them, they have many infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: ſo Satan watches them more then others, lays more ſnares for them in regard of their parts and imployments; ſo that they are more ſubject to his temptations then others. Satan hath a deſire to ſift them (as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi>) as wheat, becauſe he knows they will draw many after them; ſo that they muſt needs be ſubject to many weakneſſes and infirmities. Sometimes God makes uſe of the worſt ſort of men, even the moſt vitious and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious; firſt he changeth them, and then makes uſe of them as inſtruments of glory. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was a Veſſel of Election to carry the name of Chriſt unto the Gentiles; yet in times paſt a great perſecutor. So it pleaſeth God to make uſe of ſuch, that the excellency of the power may be of God, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49381:6"/>
            <p n="3">III. Miniſters are called Earthen Veſſels in regard of the frailty and mortality of their perſons, and earthen Veſſels are ſoon crakt and broken. Miniſters are ſubject to many infirmities of body: This Heavenly light of the Goſpel ſhineth often through Lanthorns of glaſs, which are ſoon broken. Miniſters have weak and frail bodies: <hi>Timothy</hi> had his bodily infirmities, and <hi>Trophimus</hi> was left ſick at <hi>Miletum,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.20. and <hi>Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phroditus</hi> was ſick nigh unto death, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.27. And <hi>Paul</hi> had need of <hi>Luke</hi> the Phyician, probably in regard of his weakneſs Thus the ſervants of God are ſubject to many infirmities. Beſides the reaſons in the Text, there are other reaſons why God will have it ſo.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That they may be more compaſſionate, and more ſenſible of the weakneſſes of others, for <hi>likeneſs of condition breeds ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of affection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Men are apt to pity thoſe in the like condition with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; ſo our Lord took our nature upon him, that he might pity us; he took fleſh and blood upon him, he was tempted in all things like unto us, but without ſin, that ſo he might ſuccour thoſe that are tempted: So his ſervants many of them are much tempted, which may breed in them a ſympathie of affection to others that are in ſuch a condition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God will have it ſo, that <hi>Miniſters</hi> may have the more <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience</hi> of the truths they preach to others concerning an afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed condition; thoſe that have had no ſickneſs or other affliction, cannot preach from experience of ſuch truths that concern ſuch a condition; they cannot preach ſo feelingly and ſavory as others; when they have been under affliction, they will know what af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction is, both in the nature of it, and the comforts of it, and God's gracious aſſiſtance therein; and ſo they may ſpeak com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably, and be enabled to comfort others, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God is pleaſed ſo to order it ſometimes for their humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to keep them low, that ſo they may not be lifted up by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of extraordinary manifeſtations and impartments; thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> had <hi>given him a thorn in the fleſh, that Meſſenger of Satai to buffet him, leſt he ſhould be exalted above meaſure,</hi> 2 Cor. 12.7. <hi>A thorn was given him,</hi> &amp;c. ('tis twice repeated both in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and end of the verſe) that ſo this thorn in the fleſh might
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49381:6"/>keep out pride in the heart, that ſo they may have a more low, meek, and humble frame of ſpirit, and thereby fitted and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for greater ſervices. And</p>
            <p n="4">4. That they may be alſo more conformable to thoſe they have to deal with. <hi>Iſrael</hi> deſires <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſpeak to them (and not God) why? becauſe he was like unto them, and would therefore compaſſionate them; from whom they therefore deſired to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the commands of God. Thus it pleaſeth God to deal with his ſervants, that as they may pity thoſe they have to deal with, ſo likewiſe to draw the affections of their people unto them, to make them more loving, and the more to attend on their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, ſeeing they are ſo fleeting, and going away; it pleaſed God that <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> ſhould be ſick even to death, to endear the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians</hi> more to him, chap. 2.25.28. that their love and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs may be drawn forth the more by the diſcovery of his frailty. Let us improve this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 1. Firſt, as to Miniſters, ſee how the condition is with us in our Calling; We are <hi>Earthen Veſsels,</hi> taken out of duſt; We ſhould often conſider our frailty, to make us more humble, more meek, and more compaſſionate to others, more diligent in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, that we may make amends for our frailty and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral weakneſs that are upon us: We muſt not think much of it. it being no more then in former times; it was the condition of the Apoſtles themſelves. they were Earthen Veſſels, they had ſuch weakneſſes upon them, men ſubject to the like paſſions as we.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 2. Secondly. As for the people, this they may improve in all the notions and conſiderations of an Earthen Veſſel.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In regard of the meanneſs; you muſt not eſteem the goſpel according to the <hi>veſſel,</hi> according to the diſparagement of the Veſſel; a Veſſel of diſhonor in reſpect of its matter, may be a Veſſel of honor in regard of the gold that is in it; thoſe Members of the body that are weak, and in themſelves leſs honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, we afford a great deal of honor upon them, in decking and cloathing them: So the Miniſters Work and Employment, and the Doctrines they bring, are excellent and of great uſe; when all is done, we have that we ſerve for; according to the employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we are put to, we are honorable, though outwardly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ean: Wicked and baſe men are called <hi>filij terrae,</hi> they are ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49381:7"/>earth, Job 30.8. <hi>Children of fools, yea children of baſe men; they are viler then the earth, i. e.</hi> Men of no account (as one ſaith) the earth groans under ſuch ingracious perſons; but gracious perſons are Veſſels of honor; as it was ſaid of the giants of old, ſo it may be ſaid of theſe, <hi>They are men of Renown;</hi> and ſo we ſhould eſteem of them. Worldly men look at the outſide, and ſo eſteem of them; ſo was Chriſt dealt with, <hi>Is not this the Carpenters Son?</hi> So thoſe Teachers in <hi>Corinth,</hi> endeavoured to render St. <hi>Paul his preſence weak, and his ſpeech contemptible,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.11. that ſo they might make his Miniſtry contemptible alſo. But this glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Treaſure is in Earthen Veſſels; <hi>You know</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.13. <hi>that through infirmity of the fleſh I preached the Goſpel unto you at first.</hi> This was their commendation, <hi>v.</hi> 14. <hi>But my temptation which was in my fleſh, you deſpiſed not, nor rejected, but received me as an Angel of God,</hi> even <hi>as Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All his weakneſſes, and what ever was matter of diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they did not deſpiſe, but honourably entertained him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as Chriſt himſelf. So it was the commendation of the <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13. that <hi>they received not the word as the word of man, but</hi> (as it is in truth) <hi>the word of God,</hi> looking to the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God to make it effectuall: ſo ſhould all others do upon this conſideration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Seeing Miniſters are earthen Veſſels in regard of moral in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities which adhere to them: in reſpect of their corruptions and weakneſſes judge of them as men: but eſteem of what is righteous in them; though they have great advantages againſt ſin, and be very careful againſt ſin, yet notwithſtanding they are not totally exempted and freed from ſin; as they are Miniſters, ſo they are men.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In regard that Miniſters are earthen Veſſels in reſpect of their frailty. Seeing then they are ſo frail and tranſitory, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore accordingly you ſhould make uſe of them, deal kindly and affectionately with them, in that they are quickly broken. What is ſooner broken then a Glaſs, or an earthen veſſel? Miniſters are quickly taken away, and therefore you ſhould be tender of them while you have them. Where are all the Fathers, <hi>Do the Prophets live for ever?</hi> the Word of the Lord indeed indureth for ever, but the Preacher of it doth not; the Goſpel is eternal, but the Diſpenſer is mortal; the Calling is laſting, but the Miniſter
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49381:7"/>is tranſitory; and therefore you ſhould carry your ſelves With all tenderneſs and reſpect to them: take heed of grieving their ſpirits, ſeeing they are ſo ſoon broken. Endeavour alſo to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove by them, and to get as much good as you can by them. It is a great argument <hi>to work while it is day, becauſe the night comes when no man can work:</hi> whilſt God affords means and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, make uſe of them: we are but paſſengers; therefore this is a great ground for you to endeavor to get all the good you can by your Miniſters, ſeeing they are frail.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, By way of improvement: Take notice of the ways of God as different from mans; God puts excellent treaſure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Earthen Veſſels;</hi> we keep treaſures in ſtrong holds, in the ſtrongeſt Repoſitories. God's wayes are not as our wayes, he goes another way then we do; he makes uſe of the pooreſt, meaneſt, and moſt frail creatures ſometimes; he lays aſide ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times men of greater abilities, parts and quality, and makes uſe of weaker to do this great Work. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> makes an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulation, If it be <hi>excellent treaſure,</hi> why in <hi>earthen veſſels?</hi> Therefore it is a Veſſel of Earth, becauſe an excellent Treaſure. Thus Gods ways are unſearchable. This is the improvement.</p>
            <p>Now beſides this interpretation given of it, there is another that will not be impertinent. Some underſtand by <hi>Earthen Veſſels,</hi> the expreſſions, words and phraſes of the Miniſtry, through which the doctrines and truths of the Goſpel are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed; this is agreeable to what went before: Some falſe Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers in <hi>Corinth</hi> pleaſed themſelves with eloquent and enticing words of worldly wiſdom, and ſo endeavoured to render <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching deſpicable, in regard of the plainneſs of it; therefore (ſaith the Apoſtle) we have this treaſure in earthen veſſels, <hi>h. e.</hi> familiar conveyances, that ſo we may eaſily underſtand it.</p>
            <p>Thus I have explained this Earthen Veſſel, and ſo have done with the firſt conſiderable part, <hi>viz.</hi> the diſpenſation it ſelf, <hi>This Treaſure we have in Earthen Veſſels:</hi> I come now to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. The <hi>account</hi> of this <hi>Diſpenſation, That the excellency of the power may be of God, and not of us,</hi> Which words may be conſidered two wayes.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:49381:8"/>
            <p n="1">1. Either abſolutely, as lying in themſelves. Or,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Connexively; to the words before going.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Take them abſolutely as they lie in themſelves, and two things are exhibited.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The excellency of the Goſpel and Miniſtry it ſelf, called Power.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Author and Original of it, laid down two ways, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively, <hi>of God;</hi> and negatively, <hi>not of us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The excellency of the Goſpel and Miniſtry thereof, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Power: There is a great deal of power and efficecy in the Goſpel, 'tis in its nature powerful and efficacious; ſo the Miniſtry of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. <hi>I am not aſhamed of the Goſpel of Chriſt, for it is the power of God unto ſalvation to every one that believeth.</hi> See 1 Cor. 2.4. <hi>Paul's</hi> preaching <hi>was in the demonſtration of the Spirit and of Power, &amp;c.</hi> 'Tis called the Arm of God's Power, <hi>the ſword of the Spirit,</hi> Eph. 6.17. <hi>'Tis quick and powerful, and ſharper then any two-edged ſword, piercing even to the dividing aſunder of the ſoul and ſpirit, &amp;c.</hi> Heb. 4.12. and many other places. We may conceive it to be ſo according to the various effects and conſequences of it, <hi>viz.</hi> as to
<list>
                  <item>1. Conviction.</item>
                  <item>2. Coverſion.</item>
                  <item>3. Conſolation.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis powerful in regard of conviction, 'tis a word of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction; and one part of the Work of the Miniſtry is (by the Spirits co-operation) <hi>to convince the world of ſin,</hi> to open mens eyes, to ſhew them the vileneſs of their wayes, to diſcover ſuch courſes to be ſinful; the Conſcience is awakened by the Spirit in the Miniſtry of the Word, herein 'tis powerful and efficacious: There are divers inſtances in Scripture, how powerful the Word hath been in point of conviction; in <hi>Foelix,</hi> the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> preached to him of <hi>righteouſneſs and judgement to come, &amp;c.</hi> He trembles: The Judge on the Bench trembleth at the Word de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by the Priſoner at the Bar: Sa powerful is the Miniſtry of the Word, as to diſcover our ſinfulneſs. So the Diſciples go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Emans,</hi> their hearts burnt within them when our Saviour opened to them the <hi>Prophets,</hi> &amp;c. So it was with St. <hi>Peters</hi> Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. they were pricked in the heart when they heard <hi>tha;</hi> he did preach to them in the <hi>power and demouſtration of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49381:8"/>ſpirit,</hi> and plainly diſcovered that ſin that they were more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially guilty of, and when they heard <hi>that,</hi> they <hi>were pricked in the heart, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is a word of Converſion alſo; Conviction is one thing, and Converſion is another. Sometimes men may be convinced, but yet have no change wrought in them; therefore converſion is another work, it is a turning men from darkneſs to light, from the power of Satan to God, &amp;c. to receive an inheritance among them that are ſanctified. Herein is the Word powerful, <hi>viz.</hi> in regeneration, I have begotten you (by the Word) to a lively hope, &amp;c. of his own will hath he begotten you, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is a word of comfort and conſolation, it is a powerful word, and able to comfort the heart: and the Miniſtry is very effectual herein (when ſet on by the Spirit) to quiet, ſatisfie, and pacific the conſciences of men, which declareth the remiſſion of ſin, and whoſoevers ſins are forgiven, muſt needs be comforted. Indeed it is not in the power of men to forgive ſint, yet they can ſpeak a word of comfort in ſeaſon, by the adminiſtration of the promiſes (the Spirit of God going along with them) and then they are not only declarative, but operative. Where (I ſay) it pleaſeth God to bleſs and ſanctifie the Word, it is effectual for the quieting of the mind, for pacifying of the conſcience, and ſetling of the troubled ſoul. Thus you ſee how powerful the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry is; and ſeeing it is ſo, this ſhould teach us how to behave our ſelves under it; it is powerful in it ſelf, and powerful in its diſpenſation, and hath none of that weakneſs (mentioned before) of the diſpenſer of it, <hi>I was with you</hi> (ſaith S. Paul) <hi>in much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and in fear, and intrembling,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.3.4. <hi>and my ſpeech—was in demonstration of the Spirit, and of power.</hi> Theſe may ſeem to be contradictory; but 'tis anſwered, the Word is powerful in the demonſtration of the Spirit, though delivered by one of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane weakneſs, as before is declared. This ſpiritual power we ſhould look at, and labour after; which power doth not conſiſt in matter of elocution, <hi>the enticing words of mans wiſdom,</hi> nor in matter of voice, which indeed is a good thing, and ſutable to the nature of the matter! a quick and powerful delivery is of great efficacie, and power, for the ſetting home of truths, Yet this doth not make a powerful Miniſtry; for a whiſper in the ear may cauſe a thunderbolt in the conſcience: the power lies firſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49381:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the nature of the matter; the matter conſiſts in the nature and condition of mankinde, the certainty of judgment, the neceſſity of Chriſt, the covenant of Grace, and the graces and priviledges thereof, &amp;c. Theſe carry a great deal of power and efficacie with them when they are carefully and frequently diſpenſed, and Gods ſpirit going along with them, ſo they become powerful; for the Miniſtry conſiſts not in empty notions and ſpeculations that will only tickle the ſancie, but never reach the conſcience. Moral diſcourſes, though they be of great uſe, yet if we reſt in them, they leave us as they found us. Evangelical truths (which are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold) are to be delivered in the Miniſtry. Now as the matter of the Miniſtry muſt be powerful, ſo the expreſſions muſt be power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; there ſhould be ſutableneſs of expreſſion to the matter, <hi>h. e.</hi> with gravity, ſobriety, affection, &amp;c. Strong lines make but weak preaching, and take away the efficacie; but delivering truths in the demonſtration of the ſpirit and in power, that is moſt effectual: when we ſpeak feelingly and from our hearts, it comes then (through the bleſſing of the Lord with it) with power. This is then to learn us of the Miniſtry, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Uſe.</p>
            <p>Let us be careful that the matter of our Miniſtry be powerful, ſo that the handling and diſpenſing thereof be powerful, that ſo it may come home to the conſcience; thus we ſhould deal with all; <hi>the words of the wiſe are as goads, and as nails faſtned by the Maſters of aſſemblies, &amp;c. Eccl.</hi> 12.11. So our words ſhould have a force and power in them. This as the Apoſtle ſays, is mighty and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful to the beating down of ſtrong holds, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Uſe. 2. Secondly in reference to hearers; ſeeing the Miniſtry is powerful, you muſt then ſubmit your ſelves to the power of it. Many people are Sermon proof, and think to ſtand it out againſt the power of the Word; but if it comes in power to the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, they will not be able to reſiſt it; as it is ſaid of them in the Goſpel, they were not able to reſiſt the ſpirit by which he ſpake <hi>(viz. Stephen.)</hi> And for thoſe that deſire the converſion of others, what courſe ſhould be taken by them for that end? but by good counſel, inſtruction, prayer, and good example, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to convince them, and more eſpecially to bring them to the Word and adminiſtrations thereof, which God hath ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified for this end.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49381:9"/>
            <p>So much for the excellency of the Goſpel, viz. <hi>The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the power,</hi> &amp;c. I come to the ſecond:</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Author of it, 1. Poſitively, it is of God. And 2. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatively, it is <hi>not of us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, poſitively, it is of God, and that in all the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of it, in the full extent of it, it is of God. So the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial gifts, the performances of it, and the ſucceſs of it, are all from God.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Miniſterial gifts are from God; it is he that makes us able Miniſters of the New Teſtament; there are (ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>) diverſity of gifts: to one is given <hi>the Word of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to another the Word of knowledge by the ſame Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Cor. 12.4,5,6. It is God that beſtows every good gift.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The performance alſo is from God; his grace concurs and aſſiſts therein; the habit and the act are both from him; God gives gifts to men, and he enables them to diſpence them. Miniſterial employments are not only for ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, but particular applications, and ſo need not only gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, but particular aſſiſtances; <hi>That I might be enabled</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>to fulfil the work,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the Lord ſtood by me and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened me, that my preaching might be fully accompliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is God that makes the work powerful, efficacious and ſucceſsful: Alas! when we have uſed our beſt endeavours, all the ſucceſs is from him, he muſt make it effectual; it is ſaid, our Saviour went about doing good, for God was with him, enclining him to the work, and aſſiſting him therein: So he is with all his ſervants: their gifts, employments, and ſucceſs thereof, are all of God, not of us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But it may be objected, Is all from God, and nothing from us? Are we not ſaid to concur with him? and is not then the power partly ours?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ,</hi> I anſwer, No: 'tis of God, and not of us; we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſubjects of the Miniſtry, the Recipients thereof, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons employed in the Work, and therefore are ſaid to be <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers together with God,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.1. but the power and efficacy thereof is from God alone: <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Apollo</hi> are but Miniſters, <hi>'tis God that giveth the bleſſing;</hi> 'tis not of us in two reſpects, 1. 'Tis not merited by us, 'tis not of our deſerving, nor of our procuring; 1, 'Tis not of our deſerving; the beſt &amp; moſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49381:10"/>accompliſht do not merit it: I <hi>received mercy</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) to be faithful;</hi> he accounted it a mercy to be employed, and to be faithful therein 2. 'Tis not of our own procuring, we do not obtain it by our own power, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid in the recovery of the lame man, <hi>It is not by any power and holineſs of ours, that this man is reſtored, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo it is not our gifts and induſtry onely, that will make our Miniſtry powerful; and therefore in this Work let us be looking up to God, and deſire him to aſſiſt us, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, <hi>If thou goeſt not, O Lord, up with us, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould we go hence?</hi> ſo ſay I, If the preſence of God be not with us, what can we do?</p>
            <p>And further, when we do partake of any meaſure of abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſee where we muſt determinate it; <hi>Not unto us Lord, not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, but unto thy Name be all the glory:</hi> We muſt not ſacrifice to our own net, nor give the honor to our own induſtry, but wholly give the praiſe to God, becauſe the excellency is of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But in the ſecond place, if you look upon the words re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexively, or as having their connexion to the words going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and ſo they will agree and hold together; and thus you may read them: Therefore is this <hi>Treaſure</hi> in <hi>earthen veſſels,</hi> that the <hi>excellency of the Power</hi> may be acknowledg'd to be <hi>of God,</hi> and <hi>not of us:</hi> If it were in Angels, or had we never ſo ſtrong bodies, yet the excellency of the power of God would not be ſo clearly ſeen, as it is now, being laid up in poor, frail Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels: Here's the power of God, here's the luſtre and glory of God moſt manifeſted; for ſo much the more apparently it will be ſeen to be from God, by ſo much the weaker the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, that is employed by God; therefore if any thing doth act beyond its own power, it muſt have ſome forreign powers for the producing ſuch and ſuch acts; therefore when we ſee any great matte done by poor, frail and contemptible perſons of earthen veſſels, this doth plainly ſhew the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the power to be <hi>of God,</hi> and not of <hi>men;</hi> therefore look from man to God, it is God that doth theſe things; we ſhould overlook earthen Veſſels; we ſhould (I ſay) overlook men that are theſe earthen veſſels, and look to God that makes the Miniſtry powerful in ſuch conveyences as theſe are.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49381:10"/>
            <p>Furthermore, It may ſatisfie us of the Miniſtry, in that we are Veſſels, <hi>viz.</hi> men of frailty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we are apt to be diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, and to think hardly that we are followed with ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny weakneſſes, that we have a hard matter, that when we have taken ſuch pains in the work of the Miniſtry, we ſhould be thus rewarded; but this ſhould ſatisfie us, the more weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in us, the greater honor will come to Chriſt: <hi>This Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure we have in earthen Veſſels, that the excellency of the Power may be of God, and not of us.</hi> The weaker the Veſſel, the more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor will redound to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, this may take off the ſervants of Chriſt from unwillingneſs unto thoſe works and performances which God calls them unto, by reaſon of their weakneſs: Thus it is when God calls to any work or employment, the ſervants of God are apt to plead their own inability; <hi>Moſes</hi> ſayes he is not elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent; <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſayes he is a child; <hi>Jonah</hi> ſayes he is a man of unclean lips: Thus we have their delayes, their excuſes, whereby they endeavour to diſcharge themſelves from that Work that God calls them to, by their own weakneſs; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but God refuſes ſuch excuſes; for who makes the blind to ſee, the dumb to ſpeak, but God? It is he that touched <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> lips; it is he that ſaid to <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> Do not ſay thou art a child, for <hi>I have ſent thee,</hi> &amp;c. This I ſay then is a conſideration that may encourage Miniſters in their Work, that the weaker they are, the honor and glory will redound to Chriſt; <hi>for he ſaid unto me,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>My Grace is ſufficient for thee, for my ſtrength is made perfect in weakneſs:</hi> Not that this is an encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement or argument for any to take upon them the great work of the Miniſtry, without ſufficient qualifications &amp; abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: But where there is not that degree of ability as is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, where there is a true ſenſibleneſs of their weakneſs, this may be an encouragement unto them, that God delighteth to ſhew his power in them, that by ſo much the more they are weak, ſo much honor he wil gain. For a concluſion, it comes to this, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we lay no ſtreſs upon any outward things.</p>
            <p>There is no ſtreſs or happineſs in theſe outward things; thoſe that ſeem to be of ſome concernment, as ſtrength of body, and other outward qualifications that are of remark;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49381:11"/>yet conſider, they are fading and tranſitory; this ſhould teach us in the enjoyments of outward things, a great deal of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility: Though we are Veſſels of gold in regard of the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and improvement, yet in regard of our ſelves we are Veſſels of Earth, and ſo ſhould be in reſpect of humility, Let us look upon all theſe things as given to us of God even for this very end, That we may be more ſerviceable to him and his people.</p>
            <p>So I have done with the two general parts of the words, and ſo with the whole verſe <hi>viz. We have this Treaſure in earthen Veſſels, that the excellency of the power may be of God, and not of us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Do we begin again to commend our ſelves?</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1.) <hi>or need we Epiſtles of commendation to you, or Letters of commendation from you? ye are our epiſtle in our hearts, &amp;c.</hi> But this is applicable to the preſent ſad occaſion now before us.</p>
            <p>This reverend and bleſſed man of God, Mr. <hi>James Nal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> was a perſon of great note and eminencie among us, one well known in this City, and in this place, where he ſpent his labour and pains many years. I could give large accounts and teſtimonies of him (if need were) from my own knowledge of him, having been acquainted with him many years. He was not only a Miniſter, but the ſon of a Miniſter, his birth and education ſuting together. He lookt upon it not only as an honour, but as an engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be careful to walk in thoſe ſteps ſet before him, and to continue the work of the Miniſtry begun by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious father. Certainly the children of godly and holy parents cannot come off ſo cheap in their carriages as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; they have greater accounts to make, as having grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter examples ſet before them, greater advantages of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, exhortation, &amp;c. and ſo greater engagements; this was thought on, and obſerved by him. And as he was the ſon of a Miniſter, ſo when he came to years and was fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he took upon him the Miniſtry: as he was one of great abilities, ſo accordingly he diſcharged them faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49381:11"/>and conſcienciouſly. He was a ſpiritual, powerful, conſciencious Preacher, he preached by his Life; for (as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſaith) we ſhould not only love to ſpeak truths, but we ſhould digeſt truths on our own hearts before we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them to others, and ſo they will be the more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual. He was a man of a very meek, ſweet, and humble ſpirit; a man of great humility and of great meekneſs in the midſt of great abilities, which was a great ornament in him; a man full of tenderneſs and condeſcenſion to others; a man of a very yeilding and melting frame of ſpirit, ſoon diſſolved into tears. It was the ſaying of one, that a good man is full of tears; ſo this good man was full of tears, not affected, but very real, and hearty, drawn from the fullneſs of his Spirit, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, he ſerved the Lord in much humility and many tears. This was remarkable, that in theſe times our Reverend Brother was full of tears in delivering his doctrine, which was ſutable to the age we live in, being full of ſin and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity; there is much need of a bewailing ſpirit to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail the iniquities and miſeries of the times; they that cannot bewail themſelves, need the tears of others, He was a man of great integrity, and ſingle-heartedneſs; in his exhortations he had much of the ſimplicity of Chriſt, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks. In reference to the Miniſtry, he had no worldly and baſe affections, he had no carnal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns therein; but his chief deſign was to bring ſouls home to Chriſt, that was his chief buſineſs. As the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith of himſelf, may alſo be ſaid of him, that <hi>in ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity and godly ſincerity, be had his converſation in the world, not walking in craftineſs, nor handling the word of God deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, but by the manifeſtation of the truth, commending him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to every mans conſcience in the ſight of God,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2. He was a man that had ability to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon, he was very compaſſionate to wounded ſpirits, he himſelf having been much afflicted, He was a man much in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49381:12"/>with God, and had much acquaintance with God, and was careful in improvement therein: he was a <hi>Jacob</hi> in wreſtling with God, a <hi>Moſes</hi> that ſtood in the gap, an <hi>Elijah</hi> that prayed earneſtly: the whole land was the better for ſuch a perſon, being much with God; he made many addreſſes to him, and had much holy fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity with him. And as in his publick performances he was very faithful and beneficial, ſo in his family and private he was very fruitful and ſerious. In a word (not to multiply much in this kind, you need it leſs in this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory, but onely by way of grateful memorial) there was much of God and Chriſt in him, and he was a great exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to his fellow ſervants; there was much of his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure (ſpoken of in the Text) in this earthen Veſſel; as in the matter of it, he was one of a Goſpel ſpirit; and in the conveyances of it, he had great abilities for the work of the Miniſtry, and diſcharged it with a great deal of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs. As he had this treaſure in an earthen veſſel, ſo his veſsel, his frail body was no diſparagement to him, but the advancement of the treaſure, in ſetting forth the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be of God; his outward man was much weak and worn away, but his inward man was upheld by the grace of God. His firſt work in the Miniſtry was in that place where my ſelf have relation to; he was an aſſiſtant to my Predeceſsor (being then paſt labour) Mr. <hi>Richard Couder,</hi> and performed the work ſo well, that he was exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloved of Mr. <hi>Couder,</hi> and well beloved of the Pariſh, and other places. He left a good impreſſion behind, and I found good effects by the foundation there laid. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> indeed deſired not to work there where ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had laid the foundation, but I thought it a great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage that the foundation was laid by ſuch a Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>builder. He was called into the Country to <hi>Rugby</hi> in <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wickſhire,</hi> there he continued very fruitful, and did much good. For ſome occaſion he removed, and returned into
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49381:12"/>the City, and came into this place, where he continued about 18 or 19 years, diſcharged the work of the Lord carefully. I need not ſay much of his carriage in this place, I appeal to your own conſciences. I may ſay of this ſervant of Chriſt, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of himſelf, 1 Theſs. 2.10, 11. <hi>Ye are his witneſſes, and God alſo, how ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily, and juſtly, and unblameably he behaved himſelf among you, as you know how he exhorted, and comforted, and charged every one of you (as a father doth his children) that ye would walk worthy of God, who hath called you unto his kingdom and glory.</hi> Therefore there lies an engagement upon you to walk anſwerable to the truths he delivered, and to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his ſteps, conſidering the end of his converſation. I ſhut up all in the words of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians,</hi> ch. 4.9. <hi>Thoſe things which ye have both learned, and received, and heard, and ſeen in him, Do: and the God of Peace ſhall be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
